Guide to the Witchcraft collection, unbound manuscripts, 1560-1973.
Witchcraft collection, unbound manuscripts, 1560-1973.
- Manuscripts and Documents
  - L-P
    - Leitschuh, Dr. Friedrich, to Joseph Baer and Co., forwarded to George L. Burr, 1899; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Concerns his offer to sell the documents of the witch trial of Sister Maria Renata Sänger and Hans Loder's wife [cf. these names below.]
    - Leonhardtz, Hupritch, d. 1621, defendant, circa 1621; 20 leaves (Box 4, Folder 5)
      "Verbal [confrontation] zwischen Heinrich Stein aus Oberweis [in Luxemburg], formal Clergen, und Hupricht Leonhardtz aus Oberweis Lasters Zauberei halber inquirirt [ = subject to an Inquisition trial for witchcraft]."
    - "Lijst der werken van B. Bekker...", undated; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Besides Bekker's own works, the list enumerates some 170 titles.
    - Sentença de Maria Antonia de Liveyra [contemporary copy] Trial Record (fragments), circa 1710; 10 leaves (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Report of the trial of an alleged witch who was engaged in treating kinds of human and animal diseases, using grimaces and magical signs, and pretending to "swallow the illness." She confessed to all the charges against her and was burnt.
    - Loder, Hans, defendant, 1584-1585; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Nine fragments of a trial record held in Arnstein, all addressed to the Prince-Bishop of Würtzburg.
    - Luxenburger, Johann, and Sesaner, Friedrich of Luttum (Germany), "Dreiforcher Höllenzwang", 1557?; 8 leaves and 1 sketch (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Manuscript copy of a "Höllenzwang" or book of magic containing invocations and charms intended to compel the demons to do one's will. It draws its inspiration from Dr. Faust's Wunder-Buch (1501) and includes several drawings.
    - Margareth of Körperich-Neuerburg (Luxembourg), defendant, 1600; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Her confession that she was led to become a witch by her grandmother at age 4.
    - Mafteah Shelomo/Clavicula Salomonis/Book of the Key of Solomon, undated; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 11)
      A German short copy of one of the most famous books of magic.
    - Marg[a]reta Martin of Löwenberg (Schlesien, Germany), defendant, 1619-1620; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Order to torture this woman, who was accused of magical practices and sexual intercourse with the devil, followed by a report of her unexplained death.
    - Massachussets [Colony] Courts, Essex County -- Salem Witch Trials, [1692]; 1 leaf (2 copies -- facsimiles) (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Letter from Judge William Stoughton to George Corwin, the sheriff of Essex County, ordering the execution of Bridgett Bishop, who was convicted of witchcraft, plus answering letter of Corwin confirming that the execution was completed.
      Copy from the Massachusetts State Archives.
    - Miller, Johannes, Anglican minister, [1692]; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Answer to the questions posed by Governor Joseph Dudley of New York (text in Latin).
    - Nederlandse hervorkomde kerk..., undated; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Copy of an article on Bekker.
    - Negen deelen voor en tegen B[altasar] Bekker, undated; 2 leaves and 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 16)
      List of pamphlets [1691-99] relating to the "Bekker controversy" (the furor over De Betoverde Veereld, a pamphlet published in 1691 in which Bekker attacked witch-hunting.)
    - New York State University in Binghamton, 1973; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Printed program for the conference "Witchcraft and the Occult in the Middle Ages and Early Renaissance" organized by the Center for Medieval and Early Renaissance Studies.
    - Nicholson. J.W., to Burr, 1908; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Informs Burr that he has "a facsimile copy" of the trial of Grace Sherwood.
    - Novelles voor en tegen B[altasar] Bekker, undated; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 19)
      List of 117 titles of pamphlets about Bekker (1691-1692).
    - Nürnbergische Theologen Ainhellige Antwort über etliche Puncten, die Unhulden [=demonic creatures] betreffent auff die Supplication des Raths zu Weisenburg... wie sie sich mit iren Hexen und Unhulden verhalden sollen, und was in Göttlichen heiliger Schrifft davon gegründet sey", 1590; 16 leaves (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Report and recommendations on the matter of witchcraft and witch persecution, written by six pastors from Nuremberg at the request of the local authorities in Weisenburg, 30 miles below Nuremberg.
      G.L. Burr, "The Literature of Wichcraft," in Papers of the American Historical Association, 1889, p. 61.
    - Onder het Monument von B. Bekker staat alz vogt, undated; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Inscription on Bekker's monument in Amsterdam, and list of portraits of him.
    - Pennsylvania Gazette, 1730; 4 leaves (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Copy made by Judge Gabriel Furman of an article issued on October 22, 1730 and dealing with a trial for witchcraft.
    - Picken, Magdalen, of Neuerburg (Luxembourg), defendant, 1613; 4 leaves (Box 4, Folder 23)
      The first examination and testimony of seven other convicted witches who had accused Magdalen of being one of them.
    - Pollman, Anna, defendant, 1660-64; 143 leaves (Box 4, Folder 24)
      "Untersuchungsprotokoll gegen die Ehefrau des Juergen Pollmann, Anna, geboren Nolte, in Rinteln, wegen Zauberei." With notes by G.L. Burr
    - Prütinger, Cunz, defendant, 1621; 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Order for examination by torture issued by the office of the Chancellor of the Prince-Bishop of Bamberg and Würzburg.
  - Q-S
    - Reinhard, Ursula, defendant, 1649-1654; 208 leaves (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Original documents from the trials of all three accused witches, that took place in Waltershausen in Thuringia, Germany. The first 106 leaves are sewn together in one fascicle and concern only Ursula Reinhard, who was tortured and burned. Followed by 93 loose leaves relating also to her trial, the rest is about subsequent trials of women accused by Ursula, Judith Rommelmann (2 leaves), and Caspar Hess' wife (7 leaves). With a note by G.L. Burr.
    - Rosenthal, Ludwig, May 1900; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Postcard offering for sale "a very interesting and exceedingly rare" booklet on witchcraft. Pencilled on the card is a note by G.L. Burr indicating that the book was not ordered for Cornell Library due to the price.
    - Sänger or Singerin, Maria Renata, defendant, 1749; 35 leaves (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Autograph document signed, containing: "Ratione Corporis Delicti," a brief of the case against her (leaves numbered 1-3). Three lists of questions to be asked of her (leaves numbered 4-6). Part of her examination and confession, dated February 5, 1749, and signed in her hand "Soror Maria Renata Sengerin de Mossau" (leaf numbered 7). Legal briefs discussing her alleged crimes, plus accounts of her secular trial and execution (leaves numbered 8-13). Sister Maria Renata von Mossau was a Bavarian nun at the convent of Unterzell, who was executed for heresy, witch craft, apostasy and satanism, one of the last people executed for these charges in Europe, in Würzburg in June 1749.
      Complementary sources about Maria Renata's examination are to be found at the Staatsarchiv in Würzburg with the signature HV manuscripts f. 20, f. 225, f. 267 and f. 1569. See Anton Memminger, Das verhexte Kloster: nach den Akten dargestellt, Würzburg, 1904, call number: Witchcraft BF 1583 .Z7 1749c; and "Die Praemonstratenserchorfrau Renata Singer von Mossau und ihre Sippe," in "Beiträge zur Geschichte des Bistums Regensburg 39 (2005)," Festschrift Paul Mai, p. 165-178.
    - Schlott, defendant, 1750?; 4 leaves (Box 5, Folder 4)
      AM Deposition for witchcraft against one Schlott, who was secretary for the convent of Unterzell, near Würzburg.
    - [1] Seebauer or Seebawer, K., defendant; [2] Bussbacher, Margaretha, defendant; [3] Schuster, Barbara, defendant; Eismennin, Margaretha, defendant; [4] Schneiderin, Anna, Staudtin, Anna and Magdhalena Stüberich [mother and daugher], Ottilia Dehinn, Claus Winckelmann, all from Hangenweisheim in Franconia, defendants; [5] Kühnen, defendant; [6] Künnen, Reygers, defendant; and [7] Gröling, Margaretha, defendant, 1615-30, 1905; 11 leaves + 8 leaves + 4 leaves + 2 leaves + 2 leaves+ 10 leaves + 10 leaves (Box 5, Folder 5)
      This set of manuscripts bound together contains the records of seven distinct trial records, numbered 1-7 in this catalog. The first record contains the testimony of the witnesses, and an account of the procedure of Frau Seebauer's trial and execution for witchcraft in 1629, with a short annotation by G.L. Burr ("bought for the President White's Library in September 1905") as well as two letters in German from bookseller and antiquarian Emil Hirsch from Munich, the first about this acquisition, and the second about other manuscripts documenting the history of witch-hunt in Franconia, for sale (August and September 1905). The remaining six records concern witchcraft trials that also took place in Franconia in the years 1615-1630 (2-7 in this catalog) including the last defendant's "Gut und peinliche Aussag" (statement under torture)
    - Seublin, Agnes, defendant, 1629; 12 leaves (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Six documents and a postscript scrap belonging to the trial of this Seublin of Warmbronn, near Stuttgart.
    - Spingel, Sunna, defendant, 1621; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Autograph document signed, related to a witchcraft trial held in Neuerburg, Luxembourg
    - Stein, Susanne, defendant, 6 August-20 November 1627; 4 leaves and 31 leaves and 1 leaf and 34 leaves (Box 5, Folder 8)
      "Advice" on behalf of the authorities of the Grand-Duchy of Luxembourg and indictment and complete transcript of the trial held in Neuerburg, Luxembourg. With annotations by G.L. Burr, 1887
    - Stübler, Magdalena, defendant, 1619-1620; 32 leaves (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Transcript of her witchcraft trial held at Leonberg, in Bavaria.
  - T-Z
    - Taylor, G, May 23,1926; 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Autograph letter signed to Cornell Prof. Adams, regarding a witchcraft case, as well as the "Dark Lady" of Shakespeares' Sonnets.
    - Trithemius, Johannes, Early 17th century; 6 leaves and 38 leaves (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Collection of "conjurations" or formulas of exorcism attributed to the Abbot of Spannheim, magician Trithemius (1462-1516), whose work on sorcery contained the first record of the famous folk story Dr. Faustus.
    - Wahrhafte und Umständige Nachricht von dem Zufahl, so das Jungfräulichen Closter Unterzell des Heiligen Canonischen Praemontatenser Ordens im Jahr 1749 Betroffen Hat., undated; 23 leaves (Box 6, Folder 3)
      An account of Sister Maria Renata Sänger's (or Singerin's) career from the time she entered the cloister to her trial and execution for witchcraft.
      See Box 5, Folder 3.
    - Wallys or Wallis, Mary, defendant, March 1656; 23 leaves (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Relation by Sir Richard Onsley, a clerk, who himself "had it from his credible neighbors", of a woman named Mary Wallis from Guilford, Kent, England, who was accused of having bewitched her grandson Nicholas. Contains the testimonies of villagers "[who] seemed to be sober well-bred country people." With a transcription made by William R. Johnson in 1978.
      See
      C. L'Estrange Ewen, Witch hunting and witch trials; the indictments for witchcraft from the records of 1373 assizes held for the Home Circuit A.D. 1559-1736. London: K. Paul, Trench, Trubner, 1929
      . Olin Library BF1581 .E94 W8 1971.
    - Weitluft, Nicolaus or Nicholaus, defendant, 1650; 46 leaves + 4 leaves (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Partial records containing a statement of the accusation, and a report of his examination, largely under torture, as well as of the interrogation of his accuser, beggar-boy named "Zacherlen," by the Inquisitors of the free city of Schwäbisch-Gmünd (in what is now Württemberg, Germany). The record documents the patterns of persecution, and the different strategies chosen by men and women indicted for witchcraft: in this case, Nicholaus protests that he is innocent until he is tortured and admits that indeed he has devoted himself to the devil, who visited his bedroom and turned it into a magic garden, etc.; he then retracts his confession; afterwards he admits that he is a witch, yet with the caveat that he was not really possessed. In the same "volume" is a detached leaf with the heading "Einnemen / Handlelohn." This is a record of a transfer of properties from one tenant to another, with no connection to the court trial record, except that the landlord may have been the same free city of Gmünd.
    - Wendel, Regina, defendant, 1722; 13 leaves (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Four documents from the hearings of 8 year old orphan girl named Regina Wendel, who was supposedly under the influence of the devil. Includes a report of the preliminary hearing, the examination of the defendant and witnesses, and a final decision made by a judge of Öttingen (Bavaria), who acquitted her.
    - Weyer, Lehna, Defendant, 1628; 2 leaves (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Advice given by the Luxembourg [Lutzemburg] government officials for the torture and execution of a woman who was deprived of her possessions and burned after strangulation "wegen bekannten Zauberlaster und Zauberthaten."
    - White, Andrew Dickson, September 30, 1899; 4 leaves (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Typewritten letter signed to Proffessor [sic] George L. Burr, Cornell University, discussing the contents and purchase of the records of the witchcraft trial of Maria Renata Sänger of Unterzell/Mossau.
    - White, Andrew Dickson, February 10, 1900; 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Typewritten letter signed to Professor George L. Burr, Cornell University, discussing the purchase of witchcraft trial records (Bamberg?).
    - Wick, Johann Jacob, 1522-1588, [circa 1560-1588]; 4 notebooks, 63 leaves (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Extracts made in 1888 by future historians George L. Burr and Earl Barnes [who would receive his M.S. from Cornell in 1891] from the compilation of manuscripts and print known as "Wickiana," 24 volumes kept in the Zürich Zentralbibliothek. With annotations and descriptions of illustrations by Burr.
- George Lincoln Burr catalog cards and slips (Box 7)
- Rossell Hope Robbins Encyclopedia of Witchcraft illustrations (Box 8-9)